- Hey, folks, and welcome to
the Learn UI Design lesson on consistency.
Now, I'm gonna start
by addressing probably
the biggest question I would
have, if I was sitting down
to hear a lesson about
consistency and design, which is,
"It sounds fairly abstract, how
practical is this gonna be?"
Because, the big topics
that we've covered so far,
alignment and spacing, like
they're pretty nailed down.
Right, if I tell you to
make two elements aligned,
you know when you've done it.
If I tell you to add some
white space in the elements,
well, you know, you can
see the number of pixels
between those elements.
But consistency feels a lot more abstract.
In this lesson, I'm gonna work hard to try
and really make
consistency feel practical,
and like something that
you can bring as a tool
in your design toolkit to
all the designs that you do.
Like the other fundamental
lessons, consistency
is something that you're
gonna be using across designs,
no matter what platform
you're designing for,
and no matter what type of
brand you're trying to design.
All right, with that being
said, we're gonna look
at two examples, a
mobile and a desktop one,
and let's just dive into the first.
Fundamentally, I'm really only gonna
be covering two strategies,
or two main ideas
in this lesson, and lesson
number one is something
that I call consistency first.
This is the idea, that
whenever you add a new element
to a page, like a form
control, or a text element,
or just anything at all, it's always best
to start by duplicating an existing item,
and then styling it from there.
Rather than to, you know, say,
press R for a new rectangle,
and start designing a
control from scratch.
And certainly this is the temptation,
just to press R for
rectangle, and T for text,
and start typing in something.
Let's say we had to add
a drop-down to this page.
I press Shift+V to flip
it vertically, and boom,
there, it looks like a drop-down, right?
It's great. And what if
I had to add a button?
Again, the temptation is
to press R for rectangle,
make my button.
Maybe I want to mix it
up, you know, so I'm gonna
do a ghost style button,
where there's just an outline,
rather than a full
background on the button.
And I could align these
three controls perfectly.
And I could get the spacing
between them exactly the same.
But there's still a huge
consistency issue with them.
The reason this UI looks bad, is because,
these three controls are
completely inconsistent
with one another.
Now, this example is fairly obvious.
But this sort of thing
can just creep up on you,
if you're not very conscious
about designing consistency first.
So consistency first means
I'm gonna duplicate an item
that I already have on the screen,
and I'm gonna start designing from that.
So if I want to drop-down, you
know, even though a drop-down
is not the same thing as a text box,
they're gonna be close enough
for our intents and purposes,
so I'm gonna take this text box,
and I'm gonna start modifying it.
I'm gonna switch the inner
shadow to an exterior shadow,
just so it looks like this drop-down
is now popping out of the screen.
Text boxes are more often
recessed into the screen.
We'll talk more about this in the lighting
and the shadows video.
And even before I've
added the drop-down arrow,
you can see that, essentially,
this drop-down control,
and this text box look exactly the same,
except for a shadow.
This consistency is
gonna help them feel like
they belong together.
Now, I'll grab my little
down arrow right here, and
maybe what I'll do is copy this fill color
for the default text color.
Throw it in here.
And then we'll just make
this a little bit lighter,
since it's such a big
control, relative to the size
of the text itself.
There we go.
And when we go to create a button,
we're gonna be doing exactly
the same thing again.
I'm gonna grab the
drop-down, because, a button,
like a drop-down, is often
popped out of the screen,
rather than recessed into the screen,
so that's one less thing I have to change.
How does a button look
different than a drop-down?
Well, in addition to removing
the arrow, button text,
if it is a fixed with button, button text
is almost always centered,
it's very frequently bolded.
And buttons very often also
have a background color.
And there you go, by designing
those same three controls
consistency first,
where we just duplicate
something that we already have,
and then make the bare minimum of changes,
you can see these three controls just look
so much more like they belong together.
So consistency doesn't
just help your design
make a cohesive whole, but it also makes
the design more logical.
Because, at this unconscious
level, every time a user
sees an inconsistency, let's
say it's a inconsistency
of spacing, or something like that,
they're gonna ask themselves,
why does this inconsistency exist?
Again, this is not necessarily
something we do consciously.
But the more inconsistencies
you have in your design
for no reason, like the
huge difference in space
between these two controls,
and these two controls,
the more users are gonna
pause just for a fraction
of a second, and wonder what's attempting
to be conveyed by that.
Users are just going to
assume, that if they see
a visual difference, that's also reflected
in some logical difference
that the designer
is trying to convey.
And that brings us to the
second big idea in this lesson,
which is that for every
inconsistency between anything
on your page, you should
have a rationale for it.
No inconsistencies without reason.
So whenever we make a change
from one control to a next,
we should be able to explain exactly why
we made that change.
Now, with this particular case,
it's actually kinda boring,
because, like, this drop-down
has an exterior shadow,
because, that's just
how drop-downs are done.
Like, years ago, we kind
of decided that drop-downs
would be a little popped out of the page,
text boxes would be indented in,
we'd use these little visual cues.
It's not totally hard and fast,
but it is rather across the board.
Another inconsistency is, we have
this little drop-down arrow right here.
But again, this is like
just basic convention
for how you signal to a user
that this thing is a drop-down,
you tap here, and then you're
gonna see a bunch of options.
I say drop-down, but, on mobile,
it's usually gonna slide up
from the bottom, or appear
over the rest of the screen.
And, of course, we gave this
button a colored background,
because, that's what buttons have,
it needs to draw a little attention,
because, it's kind of the
main thing on this page.
Once you fill out these controls,
this is what propels you
onto the next part of the experience.
We centered the text, we bolded it,
all because of convention.
And if I were to make further
changes, I would just want
to make sure that I always
have a reason in mind.
For instance, when I look at this,
this button actually
feels a little bit skinny.
Compared to these two controls
up here, it feels like,
for some reason, there's not less padding,
this is equal height with this and this,
but it does feel like this could use
just a little bit more height.
And so, maybe I could go and
put that in, and beef up the,
the height to, say, 49
pixels, or there abouts.
And now there's an
inconsistency in height.
It's very difficult to see, but,
even for someone who did
notice it, it is justifiable.
I'd say, "Oh, yes, this is
the main button on the page."
We do want this to be a little bit bigger.
But apart from these
little inconsistencies with
how the shadows are
done, this little arrow,
the background color on
this particular thing,
and the bold centered
text, everything else
about these controls is the same.
They have the same spacing between them.
They have the same font size in here.
These two, at least,
have the same font color.
And this is just for the hint text,
when the user picks something,
these two would remain
the same color.
All three of these controls have
the same border radius, right?
They all have a border
radius of six pixels,
a nice soft, rounded border radius.
And, of course, they
all have the same width.
So, literally, with these three controls,
I've made, as much as
possible, exactly the same.
And I've only varied the few
things that I needed to vary,
to communicate what I was
trying to communicate.
Now, one note about this.
One thing that I am saying,
is that, because, other apps
do it this way, is actually
a fairly good justification
for making an inconsistency
in your design.
Like, we put a drop-down arrow here,
because, other drop-downs
have an arrow right here.
And we put purple here,
because, a lot of other buttons
are filled in, relative to
how other controls are styled.
Good designers believe this.
But if you explicitly say
it, it can be a little bit
of a controversial
opinion among designers.
If you argue too much
for following convention,
at least among visual designers,
you might get pushback about
thinking outside the box,
or developing your personal
style, or whatever.
And I just want to say
a couple points to that.
First of all, users spend much more time
using other people's apps,
than they do using your apps.
So to the degree that your apps rely on
the same mental models, like drop-downs
have a little down arrow
on the right-hand side,
and buttons are filled
in with centered text,
to the degree that you
use those conventions,
users can piggyback on their
understanding of other apps,
to understand yours.
If I were remove this drop-down arrow,
like, that's not out of the box thinking.
That, (chuckles) that's not me
developing my personal style.
That's just me making this interface
a little bit more confusing.
Likewise, some designers
might think, oh, look,
you said button text is always centered?
Like, what if I just try
and experiment with it,
and make it left aligned here?
What if this becomes my personal style?
Like, at some point, yes,
this might be something
that you can pull off, and
this is not it right here,
this doesn't look good.
If I get this submitted
as a homework assignment,
I'm just gonna tell you
to center that text.
I do want everyone going
through this course
to eventually develop
their own personal style.
But until you can make
something that looks this good,
and clean, and simple, and
aligned, and consistent,
worry about mastering these fundamentals,
and then bring in personal style,
or unique brands in other ways.
As I discuss throughout this course,
I think typography, color
and imagery are great ways
to bring in a unique sense of brand.
I don't actually think, say,
left aligning text on a button,
or, removing the drop-down
arrow from a drop-down,
those are not good ways to do it.
All right, so does this make sense?
Like, every time we go to
add something to the screen,
we're just going to pick
something that already exists,
and duplicate it, and
style from there, right?
So if I needed some text, all of a sudden,
we'll talk about this in the sizing video,
but I'm gonna want to have as
few text sizes as possible.
So I already have these
controls that very much
have a default feeling font size,
I'm just going to keep that.
And instead of having 60%
opacity, 'cause this is kind of
the hint text that appears
before I type anything in,
I'm gonna press zero, for 100% opacity.
And then I can say, you know,
whatever explanatory text I need to.
That's designing at consistency first.
Again, let's say we need some other text.
Maybe we need like a little
legal disclaimer thing
at the bottom.
I'm gonna go grab the
nearest element that I have.
I'm gonna hold down Option.
In this case, Shift, because I just want
to move it directly down the page and
bring it right to here.
I can make the text pop up from
the bottom here, center it.
And then, again, I'm just making
the smallest possible changes.
I'm gonna make this text a
couple point sizes smaller,
and do something like maybe 14.
I'm gonna make it lighter, say
something like 70% opacity.
And that combination of making
text smaller and lighter
gives you a good secondary style.
This is one of the most
common text design patterns,
and we're gonna talk about
in the topography unit.
And we can put in some
little legal disclaimer
that really works well as secondary text,
but, also, we designed
it consistency first.
We started with the normal text we had,
and then the only three changes we made,
two of 'em, the lower size
and the lower opacity,
are unique to it being secondary text,
and then the centering
was unique to it being
kind of a footer text, or
a disclaimer sort of thing.
And that's also, again, a very
common pattern that you see.
So those are the two big ideas.
The rest of this lesson
is just repeating them.
Start consistency first.
And then only add inconsistencies,
when you have a rationale for doing so.
Now, let's look at another example.
This one is for a desktop,
and it was submitted
by Learn UI Design Student,
Lars, so, thank you, Lars.
You may notice it's all kinda blurry,
and that's on purpose.
I took an overlay layer, and
I gave it a background blur,
as you can see here of 10 pixels,
so, yeah, you can't see any
of the content directly.
But, this is intentional,
because, what I want to do,
is something called a squint test.
And this isn't totally
random, I promise it actually
does relate to consistency,
we'll get there in just a sec.
Now, a squint test, you can do it
just by squinting your
eyes, but you can also do it
with one of these overlay blur layers.
And the idea is, when
you squint your eyes,
or when you put on a blur layer,
and you look at your
design, what pops out?
You know, if you went and asked someone,
"What is this site?"
"Tell me what one does here."
"What kind of information
is on this page?"
What do they say?
And you're just looking for
the broadest level answer.
Obviously, they can't read
a single word on the page,
but, it's like, do you read things here?
Are you browsing stuff?
Are you making a purchase?
Are you entering data?
Are you editing records?
Like, what are you doing on this page?
Now, the reason I bring
this up, is because,
one of the things that
you really want to do,
is make any important
consistency in your page evident
during a squint test.
When I describe this page, I would say,
"Okay, let's start from the top-left."
I mean, there's a logo, for sure.
Then there's this, this
is like a text input box
of some sort, it looks like.
And then I have this
like repeating element.
I can tell this is a bunch
of something, because,
they are consistent
with each other, right?
It looks, they're all consistently spaced
and styled, et cetera.
I don't exactly know
what they are, though,
because, it doesn't
quite look like anything
that I've seen before.
And then, on the right-hand side here,
it looks like there's kind of two areas.
Again, just by looking at the consistency
with this like little icon,
and then this blue text,
little icon and blue text,
it looks like there's two
of some repeating element
here, and then there's two
of a different repeating
element right here.
There's some titles, there's
some explanatory text,
and there's like little
post-it notes on the side.
All right, so assuming you
kind of got the same answer
of what stuff looks like,
let's take a peek behind
the curtain here, and see
what this page really is.
So this is a research index.
It is a database of user research reports,
and study results from UX designers,
and UX researchers at
a particular company.
And the main flow of the page is,
you type in some stuff
here, you search among
the different reports
that you're looking for.
You theoretically could use these filters.
Although, Lars has said,
"In the real world,
"they don't get used."
And then you have the results
on the right-hand side.
So at kind of that squint
test level, we could say,
what we really want to
communicate is, search bar,
choose from some filters.
Since these filters are a
little repeating, multiple,
even in the squint test,
people should be able to tell
that there's like a bunch of things.
And then, look through a bunch of results.
And, actually, this original design
has a big consistency error,
in that, when we applied
that blur overlay, or did the squint test,
all of a sudden, I thought
it was very reasonable
that there were two
lists here, not just one.
This is actually one list of results.
And the blue backgrounds
are zebra striping,
where the odd numbered
rows have blue backgrounds,
and then the even numbered
rows have white backgrounds.
And there's actually just a couple
of different types of results.
This one is actually a
direct link to a file,
as you can see, and then these
are like maybe text pages
on the site, or a different type, right,
a feedback survey, or a,
I don't know, maybe a report about
some sort of options, fine.
So as we go to redesign
this, I immediately think
of a couple things.
The first is, we need to make sure
that we style these search
results consistently.
We want someone, even
at a squint test level,
to see clearly that
they're looking at a list
of four results, not two things up here,
and two things down here.
So that's one consistency issue.
But then there's kind of
this other consistency issue,
which is, we want to
style this search bar,
and these filters in a way where, again,
ideally, at even a squint test level,
because, this is the most
important stuff on the page,
people can identify it as such.
We want to make it
consistent with other sites.
Again, it might sound kind of
boring, or passe to say that.
Oh, you just want to copy off other sites?
No, no, no, no, no, no.
We want to use the conventions
that users are familiar with,
so that the moment they see these things,
even if the details are
blurred, they still know,
ah-ha, I am looking at a search bar.
So let's get started here.
I'll duplicate the frame.
And I'm actually, I'm gonna
just remove this search bar.
That...
Consistency first is a great
thing, if you have a control
that's already styled
kind of how you'd like to.
But I'm not gonna worry
about it too much, if we,
if we don't actually have
a...a good style yet.
And then we'll group these guys, because,
we'll kind of move them off to
the side of the screen here.
They could actually be
horizontally centered.
We could kind of have a
column of results right here.
And these, as well, I
will just group them,
and then maybe move them a
little bit out of the way,
until we get there.
Because, we're gonna
start from the top here.
So the first thing is,
let's create a search bar.
This content right now
has a width of 629, which,
that's not really, we're just gonna pick
a nice round number, I'll say it that way.
Does it look any better at 620, than 629?
No, but I feel better about it.
And like we talked about
in the spacing lesson,
there's a number of ways
that we could kind of show
that this search bar is
distinguished from other stuff,
like a background color change.
If the search bar is left
white, and you can see it
on a gray background, that's
one way of showing it's
kind of distinguished from its background.
We can add a...a shadow,
let's do that, for sure.
Don't worry too much
about these exact values,
we'll be talking about them shortly.
And we could also add a
bunch of border radius.
I just did that inadvertently,
but that's actually something
that a lot of search bars have.
Now, most of those search
bars aren't quite this big.
This one is pretty beefy.
But let's just try that
style, and see if it works.
Since this search bar is
big, I'm gonna go and grab,
say, material design icon.
So I do those vertically.
There we go, that could work.
And we'll put in some
text here, to search from.
Now, I actually will just
keep the same font here,
but I'm gonna give it a different color.
And, actually, let's think
about color for a second.
I'm gonna take the blue of the logo,
and I'm gonna go and
actually make them gray,
that it's kind of based
on that same blue hue,
but just a little bit more
reading like a text color,
rather than a link color.
We're gonna talk a bunch more
about this in the color unit,
though, so don't worry about it too much.
And we'll have a nice descriptive
hint text right there.
So already I can tell,
that if I were to do
a squint test right now,
you know, as long as
the search bar stood out
enough from the background
to be visible, I think
people would be able to tell,
ah, yes, it's a search bar.
Which, that actually means
one thing I want to do,
is really make sure the
search bar does stand out
from the background.
I'm actually gonna look
for a way to do that
without just using borders.
So, in this case, I'm gonna go
to back to background colors.
And if I go to the fill
of this entire frame,
I'm just gonna bump this
down a couple notches,
like really just very little.
Just to get a small sense
of kind of difference
between the search bar and the background.
And as I do this, I
might start to run into
this interesting problem, where
I've kind of got light gray
up here, and a light gray right here,
and a bright white right here,
and it's getting very gray,
and it's not actually super interesting.
Now, like one thing I could do,
is just make this whole
header blue, right?
And then, for instance,
make the text white.
But this just looks so default to me.
And again, I do actually
want to distinguish my brand
in some way, or another.
So maybe I'll do something,
like just go pick
an off the wall yellow.
I'm not gonna overthink it for now.
We're just gonna call that good
enough, and keep going here.
So I'm gonna take
this same gray that I used for text,
and I'm gonna put it into this logo now.
Awesome!
And now I feel like the
search bar is popping out
from this background a little bit more.
But, actually, part of me also
wonders, maybe we could add
like a lighter secondary
kind of sub-header,
so that the search bar popped out from,
against both of these,
and then we could have
the other content down below here.
For this sort of thing, I would just do a
very, very light kind of gray.
Something like that might work nicely.
And then this yellow has
a kind of a harsh border
with this gray.
So one thing I'll do,
is just put a little bit
of shadow there, to make it clear that
the header sort of sits above.
And I can do a similar thing here.
We'll talk more about
this in the gray lesson.
But I'll actually add just a little bit
of border around this.
I'm gonna put it on the
outside, so, actually,
that means you can only
see it on the bottom.
But then having a
slightly darker gray line
between these two lighter
gray background colors
kind of distinguishes them a bit more.
All right, so this is
kind of the overall layout
of the page here.
Of course, eventually, I will
want to get to these results.
And when I do the results,
you know, one possible way
of styling them is, now that I
have a light gray background,
I can use white as a card color.
We're gonna give this a much
more subdued border radius,
like six, but then say
each result is it's,
is in its own separate card here.
This seems pretty light
and airy right now,
but we will have some text on here,
and I think it'll become more apparent
what the user is looking at.
So this is sort of the
longer term goal here.
But before we get there,
we have to worry about
the filters, right?
Because, like we said, when
you're going through this,
you should see search
box, here's some filters,
here's a list of results.
So I'm, again, I'm gonna
think consistency first here.
Just like I dragged this,
to start making the card,
and so, that these things
match in shadow and everything,
I'm gonna drag this, to start
making some of these filters.
Now, I'm just gonna do like a
very, very simplistic version
of what filters can look like.
I'm not gonna think too much about
the ideal user experience of
these, just for the sake of
we're focusing on visual design right now.
Lars did say, I think some
of the more important fields
were authors, so we might
imply that these are filters
by saying that currently
showing all authors.
And I'm gonna press Shift+A,
to do an auto layout,
it kind of gets a nice,
consistent margin around here.
And, we'll have one that says all dates,
I think that was another one of
the most important categories.
And, finally,
(types on keyboard)
all orgs.
And then, if I choose to add more,
I can actually make another auto layout
out of all three of these,
by pressing Shift+A.
And then, I can easily create
more just by selecting one
of these individually, holding
down Option, and, boop,
there's my fourth, it's in line.
They all have a nice
consistent spacing between them
of eight pixels.
If I thought this was gonna be unclear,
I could label it, but
I'm not particularly sure
that that's necessary right now.
The general idea is, when I
clicked into one of these,
I would see a little
box that then allowed me
to filter by specific authors,
or, you know, whatever,
contains versus matches,
whatever filtering controls
we need for these.
And then, when one of these
was active, it might be bold,
or colored, or it would be
made inconsistent in some way,
so as to make it clear what was happening.
We could actually take a stab at that.
You know, we could say
(types on keyboard)
something like, Date 2020 is
one of the active filters.
We'd move it up to the front here.
Change the color a little bit.
I might do something, like grab this gray.
Or actually, sorry, what I
really want is this theme blue,
let's see how well this works.
Not well with white.
But that actually looks much better.
Now, one thing that's become clear,
is now that I have three of these filters,
because, they have these big
light shadows all around 'em,
this whole area feels like it has
just a bit too much shadowing.
I'm gonna kind of rein
these back in a little bit.
This'll also make the filters
look not as far popped out
of the screen as the search bar itself,
which checks out with me.
All right, now the next
thing I want to add,
is this kind of five items in this index,
like basically saying
there's five search results.
We're gonna do this consistency
first, so I'm gonna grow,
go in here, I'm gonna grab this textile.
Of course, it goes somewhere
else on the screen,
I don't need it.
But we'll throw it right here,
which is a very typical spot
for these sort of messages to go.
Since it's a label on results,
I think I might actually,
generally, want it a bit closer
to the results themselves,
than to the filters above.
That's the idea of
internal spacing being less
than external spacing.
And this is all feeling
good enough, where I think
we can actually just start
working on the cards.
Now, when you're thinking
about consistency
in some sort of repeating element,
one of the most important
things to consider,
is how to be inconsistent.
Because, we're not gonna style
each of these exactly the same.
When we decide what treatment
to use for one of these cards,
or for all of them, we have to say, like,
what is the most important
difference between 'em
we're trying to convey?
And there's a bunch of
different differences, right?
They have different authors.
This is Roger Parker, this is Jane Smith.
These two don't even really seem
to have one particular author.
Lars did say, "Basically,
no search results
"actually have key
learnings, it's very rare."
So we're not gonna make
too much of a deal of this.
But I think, honestly, overall,
despite all these differences
in terms of like the region,
and the division, and the
date, and the author, and the,
the explanatory text, the
biggest difference between these,
is these two are basically
PowerPoint file downloads,
and these link off to something else.
And so, what I want to do,
is have a very similar style
of display, but it should be
super, super apparent to a user
that these are going to, like,
just download a file straightaway.
And then these are gonna link you in a,
kind of a more normal web way.
So let's just start by
designing the first one,
but paying attention to
this idea that we will need
to have some sort of PowerPoint icon,
which I dropped right here.
Actually, let's just throw that on first.
It's way too big right now,
so let's jump down to something like
64 pixels, or, even lower.
It doesn't need to be particularly big
to tell users what it's all about.
Now, it looks like there's
fundamentally three lines
that I need to include here.
But I'm gonna want to include
'em in a way where I can
be consistent between the two
different major card types.
Definitely, there's a title
here, and there's a title here,
so that's apples to apples comparable.
Then there's kind of this subtitle stuff,
with some other information.
Lars has said only a
few of these properties
are actually really important,
so we'll just display those.
And then it looks like this one has,
you know, maybe some tags, or something,
sustainability, clean
tech, green building.
This one has nothing of
that sort, and then these,
rather than having tags, actually have
some other content about what was in
the feedback survey, or
what was studied here
in this "Upgrade Flow Options" report.
So if the major inconsistency
between these different types
of cards is whether you're
downloading a PowerPoint file,
or going to another link,
the major consistency is,
I think we can kind of display most
with about three lines of text.
And so, that means a lot of
this stuff is gonna get cut off.
But, again, if only a very,
very slim number of results
have this, that may not
really be much of a problem.
(types on keyboard)
All right, see what I did here?
Even though there's gonna
be three lines of text,
that will style in different ways.
Thinking consistency first, I
copied our default text style,
and just pasted it at three times.
Now, a title?
For sure, that's gonna be bold.
Do we need to make it bigger?
I'm not even sure about that yet.
Let's wait and see here.
Part of me thinks we
should apply that same sort
of secondary style, where
we make something smaller
and lighter, to this here.
But, if we actually have
a lotta text down here
in that secondary style, it's
gonna be kinda tough to read.
So maybe what makes the most sense,
is to apply the secondary style to this.
There we go, to me,
this looks pretty good.
But one thing that we're gonna cover
in the lists and tables lesson, is that
you can never just evaluate
one list item alone.
You always have to duplicate it,
get it going a couple times.
And then you'll have a much better idea
of if that style is working out for you.
So I know the last two of
these are not PowerPoints,
so I'll remove those.
But then I'll just get some
of the text working first.
And this is looking good.
I think some of the last
things I want to do,
are just include some little
icon right here that says
this is just a normal
document that you can go to.
So I'm gonna, again, be consistent
with what icon I'm using,
go to the material design icon library,
and just start searching around, document,
it doesn't have it.
File, this one actually might be about
the closest we can get.
What I want to do, is have
this roughly centered here.
And, I'm just going start
by giving it the same color
as everything else, kind
of this default color.
Maybe I'll make it a
little more blue, though,
just so it feels more interesting.
I guess one thing I could have done,
is copied straight from here.
But, does that look too dark?
Something like that might work great.
Not really trying to overthink it here.
And, there we go. The last
thing I think I want to do,
is now that we've defined
the secondary style,
I kind of want to make
this a little bit lighter,
and potentially even a
little bit smaller, as well.
It's a label that should pop
up the moment I look for it.
But, as long as I'm not looking for it,
it's not super important,
and doesn't need my attention
as much as some of the
other text on the page.
So there we have it,
there's the before-after.
Overall, I'm super-pleased
with how this went.
And that makes sense, because,
we followed such a solid process here.
We really tried to be consistent about
having filters look like other filters.
And you can see this, if I
go to a site like airbnb.com,
this is exactly what
their filters look like.
If you're familiar with this,
and you've used this before,
this isn't gonna take
you too much by surprise.
Then we also tried to be really consistent
about how we styled the cards.
Not only styling them
as similarly as possible
from card to card, but
also being very logical
about where the differences were.
In this case, it's super-easy to see
what is a PowerPoint document,
and what is a normal web link.
And yet, at the same time,
we keep a very clean,
neat appearance.
Now, as a fun kinda test, we could go back
to that squint test idea,
and overlay this result.
To me, I think it's much more clear
that we're looking at a
search bar, with some filters,
and a list of results in
this one, than it is here.
And I don't want to just
flatter myself here, I mean,
you can email me if you think I'm wrong.
I also asked my wife, I
said, "What is this site?"
With the squint test in place.
And she said, "Oh, it's a
search bar and some results."
And I said, "What's this one?"
And she said, "Oh, it's
a government site."
So, (chuckles) there you go.
That just shows you should be careful
if you give me a design
to redesign of yours.
And that wraps it up
for consistency, folks,
hope you enjoyed it.
So if you take two things
away from this lesson,
remember, number one, consistency first.
Any time you go and start
creating a new form control,
a new piece of text, whatever
it is on your design,
start by duplicating something else,
the most similar element
that's already on the page,
and then make only the
changes you need to, right?
So item number one, consistency first.
Item number two, only make
inconsistencies with reason,
have a rationale for
everything you change.
A lot of times that
rationale is, this is just
how you make this thing
look like what it should be.
But, you will be hearing a
lot of these little rationales
and ideas all throughout this course.
If they don't come easily, don't worry,
as you watch more videos,
they will come up.
All right, take a look
at the homework below,
and we'll see you in the next video.